Show me the computer that did it.
[Translation failed] Show me the computer that did it.
That's it. That's where the world's
[Translation failed] That's it. That's where the world's
largest reversible prime was found in
[Translation failed] largest reversible prime was found in
there.
[Translation failed] there.
Today, ready? Breaking math news. New
[Translation failed] Today, ready? Breaking math news. New
prime. It's not often we get a new
[Translation failed] prime. It's not often we get a new
prime. Well, a new prime. It's a
[Translation failed] prime. Well, a new prime. It's a
record-breaking length of prime, but
[Translation failed] record-breaking length of prime, but
only of a certain type of prime. And
[Translation failed] only of a certain type of prime. And
it's the same type of prime as 1,21.
[Translation failed] it's the same type of prime as 1,21.
That is a prime number. We call it a
[Translation failed] That is a prime number. We call it a
prime. But more than that, this is a
[Translation failed] prime. But more than that, this is a
special type of prime. This is an M Herp
[Translation failed] special type of prime. This is an M Herp
prime. And do you want to have a guess
[Translation failed] prime. And do you want to have a guess
what an EMURP or MER prime is?
[Translation failed] what an EMURP or MER prime is?
>> Look, it says on the box, doesn't it?
[Translation failed] >> Look, it says on the box, doesn't it?
>> It really does.
[Translation failed] >> It really does.
>> It's a prime backwards. There you are.
[Translation failed] >> It's a prime backwards. There you are.
Very, very funny mathematicians. Well
[Translation failed] Very, very funny mathematicians. Well
done. Haha. It's a prime, which is a
[Translation failed] done. Haha. It's a prime, which is a
prime in both directions. So the number
[Translation failed] prime in both directions. So the number
1 0 2 1 is also prime. So because the
[Translation failed] 1 0 2 1 is also prime. So because the
digits forward and the digits backwards
[Translation failed] digits forward and the digits backwards
are prime, it's an emote prime for prime
[Translation failed] are prime, it's an emote prime for prime
backwards. It's pretty special.
[Translation failed] backwards. It's pretty special.
>> That's nice.
[Translation failed] >> That's nice.
>> Also works for 1,193.
[Translation failed] >> Also works for 1,193.
I looked a couple up just so I was
[Translation failed] I looked a couple up just so I was
ready. Now you can see there's already
[Translation failed] ready. Now you can see there's already
going to be some constraints on what
[Translation failed] going to be some constraints on what
makes an EMP because it's got to be odd
[Translation failed] makes an EMP because it's got to be odd
beginning and end. Can't be five
[Translation failed] beginning and end. Can't be five
beginning and end. So you you're going
[Translation failed] beginning and end. So you you're going
to rule out a lot like being prime is
[Translation failed] to rule out a lot like being prime is
not super rare.
[Translation failed] not super rare.
>> What about two?
[Translation failed] >> What about two?
>> Two.
[Translation failed] >> Two.
>> What about two?
[Translation failed] >> What about two?
>> Do you count two? I count two.
[Translation failed] >> Do you count two? I count two.
>> Yeah.
[Translation failed] >> Yeah.
>> Two is the special prime.
[Translation failed] >> Two is the special prime.
>> So why it can be special in this regard
[Translation failed] >> So why it can be special in this regard
as well, isn't it?
[Translation failed] as well, isn't it?
>> That's the same forward and backwards.
[Translation failed] >> That's the same forward and backwards.
>> Mhm.
[Translation failed] >> Mhm.
>> All one digit primes primes. Anything
[Translation failed] >> All one digit primes primes. Anything
palendroic
[Translation failed] palendroic
[Translation failed] 101
palendroic prime. I I think to be emurp
[Translation failed] palendroic prime. I I think to be emurp
you really it has to be not a palendrome
[Translation failed] you really it has to be not a palendrome
but stays prime both ways. I feel like
[Translation failed] but stays prime both ways. I feel like
that's I think palendromes are their own
[Translation failed] that's I think palendromes are their own
special thing. So I would say two is a
[Translation failed] special thing. So I would say two is a
palmic prime but these these are
[Translation failed] palmic prime but these these are
special. So anyway to complete that 3
[Translation failed] special. So anyway to complete that 3
911 is also prime. So you can check
[Translation failed] 911 is also prime. So you can check
that.
[Translation failed] that.
>> Nice.
[Translation failed] >> Nice.
>> Um and a record-breaking
[Translation failed] >> Um and a record-breaking
emote prime was discovered.
[Translation failed] emote prime was discovered.
It has 10,01
[Translation failed] It has 10,01
digits, beating the previous record of
[Translation failed] digits, beating the previous record of
10,07
[Translation failed] 10,07
digits.
[Translation failed] digits.
>> So, four more.
[Translation failed] >> So, four more.
>> Four more. Four more digits.
[Translation failed] >> Four more. Four more digits.
>> Okay.
[Translation failed] >> Okay.
>> It's not a lot. And would you believe I
[Translation failed] >> It's not a lot. And would you believe I
have already memorized all 10,1 digits?
[Translation failed] have already memorized all 10,1 digits?
>> I I would believe that.
[Translation failed] >> I I would believe that.
>> You
[Translation failed] >> You
would believe that. And you believe it
[Translation failed] would believe that. And you believe it
for a very good reason that it's very
[Translation failed] for a very good reason that it's very
easy to memorize. It's So, originally I
[Translation failed] easy to memorize. It's So, originally I
was like, "Oh my goodness." uh massive
[Translation failed] was like, "Oh my goodness." uh massive
record-breaking emote prime and when I
[Translation failed] record-breaking emote prime and when I
got the news so the person Stefan who
[Translation failed] got the news so the person Stefan who
found it emailed me to say found a new
[Translation failed] found it emailed me to say found a new
prime and I'm like I love the fact I am
[Translation failed] prime and I'm like I love the fact I am
the lightning rod for people to email
[Translation failed] the lightning rod for people to email
when they discover new primes and I
[Translation failed] when they discover new primes and I
happen to be in a van with alien of
[Translation failed] happen to be in a van with alien of
number file fame we both got very
[Translation failed] number file fame we both got very
excited we're like how long would it
[Translation failed] excited we're like how long would it
take to say it could you then reverse
[Translation failed] take to say it could you then reverse
you saying it to still say a prime
[Translation failed] you saying it to still say a prime
number yes and then we realized saying
[Translation failed] number yes and then we realized saying
it would be super boring. So, without
[Translation failed] it would be super boring. So, without
dragging it out any longer, let's have a
[Translation failed] dragging it out any longer, let's have a
look at this new record-breaking prime.
[Translation failed] look at this new record-breaking prime.
>> Let's do it.
[Translation failed] >> Let's do it.
>> It is
[Translation failed] >> It is
>> Hey, what are you looking at? You said
[Translation failed] >> Hey, what are you looking at? You said
you'd memorized it.
[Translation failed] you'd memorized it.
>> Let me rephrase that. Uh, I could
[Translation failed] >> Let me rephrase that. Uh, I could
memorize it.
[Translation failed] memorize it.
>> Okay,
[Translation failed] >> Okay,
>> let me show you the I'll show you the
[Translation failed] >> let me show you the I'll show you the
number and you get the idea. It is 3
[Translation failed] number and you get the idea. It is 3
bill867,632,931*
[Translation failed] bill867,632,931*
10 to the power of 10,0001 plus one.
[Translation failed] 10 to the power of 10,0001 plus one.
What you have here is 10 to the power of
[Translation failed] What you have here is 10 to the power of
10,0001 means a one followed by 10,01
[Translation failed] 10,0001 means a one followed by 10,01
zeros and then you multiply this on the
[Translation failed] zeros and then you multiply this on the
front. So what that ends up looking like
[Translation failed] front. So what that ends up looking like
is 3 8 6 7 6 3 2 93 1. Then you start 00
[Translation failed] is 3 8 6 7 6 3 2 93 1. Then you start 00
0 dot dot dot dot dot zero's for day 0
[Translation failed] 0 dot dot dot dot dot zero's for day 0
0. But then the plus one comes in
[Translation failed] 0. But then the plus one comes in
clutch. Boom. So that actual stretch in
[Translation failed] clutch. Boom. So that actual stretch in
the middle there that is going to be uh
[Translation failed] the middle there that is going to be uh
10,000 zeros.
[Translation failed] 10,000 zeros.
That's the easiest bit to remember. So,
[Translation failed] That's the easiest bit to remember. So,
if you lock in these digits on the top
[Translation failed] if you lock in these digits on the top
and then say zero 10,000 times and then
[Translation failed] and then say zero 10,000 times and then
say one, you're done. The question now
[Translation failed] say one, you're done. The question now
is, well, hang on. It's got to be a
[Translation failed] is, well, hang on. It's got to be a
reversible prime. So, you just flip the
[Translation failed] reversible prime. So, you just flip the
whole thing around. Now, you can write
[Translation failed] whole thing around. Now, you can write
it out the fancy way. So, the fancy way
[Translation failed] it out the fancy way. So, the fancy way
is 10. So, now the 10,10,
[Translation failed] is 10. So, now the 10,10,
so that's going to give us 1 followed by
[Translation failed] so that's going to give us 1 followed by
10,10 zeros. So that's 10,011 digits
[Translation failed] 10,10 zeros. So that's 10,011 digits
including that lead one which is the
[Translation failed] including that lead one which is the
record-breaking length. But then on the
[Translation failed] record-breaking length. But then on the
end you add the reverse of this. So then
[Translation failed] end you add the reverse of this. So then
you add on 1 3 9 2 oops 3 6 7 6 8 3 and
[Translation failed] you add on 1 3 9 2 oops 3 6 7 6 8 3 and
that gives you your number. So, so just
[Translation failed] that gives you your number. So, so just
to you know for complete that's now a
[Translation failed] to you know for complete that's now a
one followed by a 0 0 0 dot dot dot dot
[Translation failed] one followed by a 0 0 0 dot dot dot dot
dot 0 0 1 3 9 2 3 6 7 6 8 3 and done.
[Translation failed] dot 0 0 1 3 9 2 3 6 7 6 8 3 and done.
There you go.
[Translation failed] There you go.
>> Wow.
[Translation failed] >> Wow.
>> Isn't that special?
[Translation failed] >> Isn't that special?
>> It's good.
[Translation failed] >> It's good.
>> Yeah.
[Translation failed] >> Yeah.
>> Who uh how was this done? Who like was
[Translation failed] >> Who uh how was this done? Who like was
it done with a I'm assuming it was done
[Translation failed] it done with a I'm assuming it was done
with a computer.
[Translation failed] with a computer.
>> It's done with a computer. So we have
[Translation failed] >> It's done with a computer. So we have
talked about this many years ago on
[Translation failed] talked about this many years ago on
number file um prime grid cuz not many
[Translation failed] number file um prime grid cuz not many
people do prime grid. I mean I do as I
[Translation failed] people do prime grid. I mean I do as I
speak. There is a computer in my office
[Translation failed] speak. There is a computer in my office
that I built solely to run prime grid
[Translation failed] that I built solely to run prime grid
and I used to have a server called
[Translation failed] and I used to have a server called
Calculus Prime which is very sadly was
[Translation failed] Calculus Prime which is very sadly was
decommissioned when I moved office. It
[Translation failed] decommissioned when I moved office. It
was getting very old and adding a
[Translation failed] was getting very old and adding a
trivial amount of compute power these
[Translation failed] trivial amount of compute power these
days. And someone called Stefan got
[Translation failed] days. And someone called Stefan got
involved in Prime Grid. Got very excited
[Translation failed] involved in Prime Grid. Got very excited
about different types of primes.
[Translation failed] about different types of primes.
Realized that maybe they could break the
[Translation failed] Realized that maybe they could break the
record for emers. So they wrote their
[Translation failed] record for emers. So they wrote their
own prime civ. So, it's a way of like
[Translation failed] own prime civ. So, it's a way of like
you use numbers that aren't primes to
[Translation failed] you use numbers that aren't primes to
kind of build up where all the primes
[Translation failed] kind of build up where all the primes
must be because all the multiples of the
[Translation failed] must be because all the multiples of the
previous primes get removed. You civ
[Translation failed] previous primes get removed. You civ
them out. They wrote their own terrible
[Translation failed] them out. They wrote their own terrible
prime civ their words, not mine, in CC
[Translation failed] prime civ their words, not mine, in CC
code. And then they also used some of
[Translation failed] code. And then they also used some of
the offthe-shelf prime
[Translation failed] the offthe-shelf prime
algorithms on Prime Grid. So, if you go
[Translation failed] algorithms on Prime Grid. So, if you go
on Prime Grid, there's a page which is
[Translation failed] on Prime Grid, there's a page which is
basically excellent prime algorithms and
[Translation failed] basically excellent prime algorithms and
they picked two of those and used them
[Translation failed] they picked two of those and used them
as well. And then they just started
[Translation failed] as well. And then they just started
searching. And this is a clever way of
[Translation failed] searching. And this is a clever way of
doing it. So you search for different
[Translation failed] doing it. So you search for different
combinations of these and then different
[Translation failed] combinations of these and then different
lengths of zeros and then just chuck a
[Translation failed] lengths of zeros and then just chuck a
one on the other end. And if you find
[Translation failed] one on the other end. And if you find
one that works this way around, you
[Translation failed] one that works this way around, you
whoop and you check it the other way
[Translation failed] whoop and you check it the other way
around. And these are nice compact ways
[Translation failed] around. And these are nice compact ways
to to phrase them. You set that code
[Translation failed] to to phrase them. You set that code
running. You wait a very long time. I
[Translation failed] running. You wait a very long time. I
actually don't know how long Stefan was
[Translation failed] actually don't know how long Stefan was
waiting. And it spits out one of these
[Translation failed] waiting. And it spits out one of these
and you email it to me. That
[Translation failed] and you email it to me. That
seems to be the entire
[Translation failed] seems to be the entire
journey. I thought about emailing Matt
[Translation failed] journey. I thought about emailing Matt
right at the beginning. I was like,
[Translation failed] right at the beginning. I was like,
"Yeah, okay. I will I will do it
[Translation failed] "Yeah, okay. I will I will do it
someday." Right. F first person I I told
[Translation failed] someday." Right. F first person I I told
was my girlfriend. She was like, "Cool."
[Translation failed] was my girlfriend. She was like, "Cool."
>> Yeah. She
[Translation failed] >> Yeah. She
>> does. She really think it's cool or is
[Translation failed] >> does. She really think it's cool or is
she into this stuff?
[Translation failed] she into this stuff?
>> She she's not into this stuff. She She
[Translation failed] >> She she's not into this stuff. She She
thinks it's it's pretty cool that I
[Translation failed] thinks it's it's pretty cool that I
found something, but um she really can't
[Translation failed] found something, but um she really can't
um yeah see the the nerdy value of of
[Translation failed] um yeah see the the nerdy value of of
these kind of numbers.
[Translation failed] these kind of numbers.
>> Was this lowhanging fruit?
[Translation failed] >> Was this lowhanging fruit?
In the in the search for prestigious
[Translation failed] In the in the search for prestigious
primes, you said
[Translation failed] primes, you said
>> Yes. Yes. You
[Translation failed] >> Yes. Yes. You
you can think of numbers and primes as
[Translation failed] you can think of numbers and primes as
like an orchard and not all trees are
[Translation failed] like an orchard and not all trees are
equal and like the just the generic
[Translation failed] equal and like the just the generic
prime tree. That's amazing. And everyone
[Translation failed] prime tree. That's amazing. And everyone
wants to get the get the fruit off that
[Translation failed] wants to get the get the fruit off that
tree.
[Translation failed] tree.
>> That's the magic far away
[Translation failed] >> That's the magic far away
>> magic far away tree. Um but everyone's
[Translation failed] >> magic far away tree. Um but everyone's
cleared the branches. Like there's only
[Translation failed] cleared the branches. Like there's only
a little bit of fruit right at the top.
[Translation failed] a little bit of fruit right at the top.
But then
[Translation failed] But then
>> there's an infinite amount of fruit.
[Translation failed] >> there's an infinite amount of fruit.
There's an infinite amount of fruit
[Translation failed] There's an infinite amount of fruit
above the threshold. Correct. Correct.
[Translation failed] above the threshold. Correct. Correct.
It's a very generous tree in that
[Translation failed] It's a very generous tree in that
regard. But then there are other trees
[Translation failed] regard. But then there are other trees
with less appealing fruit that may be
[Translation failed] with less appealing fruit that may be
lower down. And what you're going to do
[Translation failed] lower down. And what you're going to do
is trade off the appealingness of the
[Translation failed] is trade off the appealingness of the
fruit with the distance from the ground.
[Translation failed] fruit with the distance from the ground.
And I wouldn't say this was lowhanging
[Translation failed] And I wouldn't say this was lowhanging
fruit. I'd say medium medium low, but
[Translation failed] fruit. I'd say medium medium low, but
very cool type of number. I mean, we're
[Translation failed] very cool type of number. I mean, we're
making a video about it. People are
[Translation failed] making a video about it. People are
finding numbers all the time and we
[Translation failed] finding numbers all the time and we
don't make a video. But this I was like,
[Translation failed] don't make a video. But this I was like,
that's cool. People wouldn't know about
[Translation failed] that's cool. People wouldn't know about
that. and it was within reach of Stefan
[Translation failed] that. and it was within reach of Stefan
just being an enthusiast putting some
[Translation failed] just being an enthusiast putting some
code together and being able to to find
[Translation failed] code together and being able to to find
one. And what I really like about it
[Translation failed] one. And what I really like about it
other than like it's a fun number and it
[Translation failed] other than like it's a fun number and it
was an enthusiast who decided to give it
[Translation failed] was an enthusiast who decided to give it
a go. It was a combination of
[Translation failed] a go. It was a combination of
self-written code or be in C which is
[Translation failed] self-written code or be in C which is
far more efficient than Python not to
[Translation failed] far more efficient than Python not to
throw shade on Python um and the
[Translation failed] throw shade on Python um and the
shoulders of giants. So taking the
[Translation failed] shoulders of giants. So taking the
giants can reach further up the tree.
[Translation failed] giants can reach further up the tree.
And so by taking the uh algorithms
[Translation failed] And so by taking the uh algorithms
already developed for other bits of
[Translation failed] already developed for other bits of
prime grid and applying them with their
[Translation failed] prime grid and applying them with their
own civ, Stephan was able to do this.
[Translation failed] own civ, Stephan was able to do this.
And that collaboration of prime grid
[Translation failed] And that collaboration of prime grid
which is just like a huge collaborative
[Translation failed] which is just like a huge collaborative
amount of human intellect gone into it
[Translation failed] amount of human intellect gone into it
and a little lone warrior getting the
[Translation failed] and a little lone warrior getting the
fruit. Great.
[Translation failed] fruit. Great.
>> You really ran with that fruit analogy.
[Translation failed] >> You really ran with that fruit analogy.
>> Thank you. I didn't realize I didn't
[Translation failed] >> Thank you. I didn't realize I didn't
realize how much how much juice was
[Translation failed] realize how much how much juice was
available in that analogy.
[Translation failed] available in that analogy.
>> Show me the computer that did it.
[Translation failed] >> Show me the computer that did it.
It's that little one there. Is that
[Translation failed] It's that little one there. Is that
under the
[Translation failed] under the
>> Yeah, it's it's the mini computer with
[Translation failed] >> Yeah, it's it's the mini computer with
like uh eight cores.
[Translation failed] like uh eight cores.
>> That's it. That's where the world's
[Translation failed] >> That's it. That's where the world's
largest reversible prime was found in
[Translation failed] largest reversible prime was found in
there.
[Translation failed] there.
>> Yeah.
[Translation failed] >> Yeah.
>> Do you prefer calling them reversibles
[Translation failed] >> Do you prefer calling them reversibles
or e-urpers?
[Translation failed] or e-urpers?
>> I don't know. Um, I just stick with the
[Translation failed] >> I don't know. Um, I just stick with the
wording reversible.
[Translation failed] wording reversible.
>> Are there an infinite number of emers
[Translation failed] >> Are there an infinite number of emers
according to Wikipedia? Open problem. We
[Translation failed] according to Wikipedia? Open problem. We
don't know. This could be the final
[Translation failed] don't know. This could be the final
e-urper.
[Translation failed] e-urper.
Imagine. Wouldn't that be special? Now,
[Translation failed] Imagine. Wouldn't that be special? Now,
that would be top of the tree. We don't
[Translation failed] that would be top of the tree. We don't
know how big the tree is in this case.
[Translation failed] know how big the tree is in this case.
This could be the last run. Isn't that
[Translation failed] This could be the last run. Isn't that
incredible? So, yeah. Uh, open problem.
[Translation failed] incredible? So, yeah. Uh, open problem.
You could try and find a bigger one or I
[Translation failed] You could try and find a bigger one or I
don't know if there's a way. There might
[Translation failed] don't know if there's a way. There might
be some kind of statistical argument
[Translation failed] be some kind of statistical argument
about what percentage of primes, but if
[Translation failed] about what percentage of primes, but if
it was that easy, someone would have
[Translation failed] it was that easy, someone would have
done the proof by now. There might be. I
[Translation failed] done the proof by now. There might be. I
don't know how hard that would be to be
[Translation failed] don't know how hard that would be to be
honest. Again, a lot of lowhanging
[Translation failed] honest. Again, a lot of lowhanging
proofs like that are done. And the fact
[Translation failed] proofs like that are done. And the fact
that Wikipedia says no one's managed to
[Translation failed] that Wikipedia says no one's managed to
prove one way or the other yet probably
[Translation failed] prove one way or the other yet probably
means it's a slightly difficult proof to
[Translation failed] means it's a slightly difficult proof to
be able to do. So, there you are. That's
[Translation failed] be able to do. So, there you are. That's
possibly the final emote.
[Translation failed] possibly the final emote.
I reckon there's another one. Nah, I
[Translation failed] I reckon there's another one. Nah, I
think that's it. Here on number five, we
[Translation failed] think that's it. Here on number five, we
show you a lot of freakish cool things
[Translation failed] show you a lot of freakish cool things
in mathematics like biggest prime
[Translation failed] in mathematics like biggest prime
numbers. But to make these discoveries,
[Translation failed] numbers. But to make these discoveries,
you need the foundations. You need to
[Translation failed] you need the foundations. You need to
understand how mathematics works, how to
[Translation failed] understand how mathematics works, how to
code, all that kind of stuff. And for
[Translation failed] code, all that kind of stuff. And for
me, you know, it's been a long time
[Translation failed] me, you know, it's been a long time
since I learned that back at high
[Translation failed] since I learned that back at high
school. And if you want to get those
[Translation failed] school. And if you want to get those
skills or you want to get them back, a
[Translation failed] skills or you want to get them back, a
really good place to go is today's
[Translation failed] really good place to go is today's
episode sponsor, Brilliant.
[Translation failed] episode sponsor, Brilliant.
Brilliant is jam-packed with courses
[Translation failed] Brilliant is jam-packed with courses
that are highly interactive, engaging,
[Translation failed] that are highly interactive, engaging,
and frankly just good fun. You'll get
[Translation failed] and frankly just good fun. You'll get
smarter with a smile on your face.
[Translation failed] smarter with a smile on your face.
But the thing I find exciting is that
[Translation failed] But the thing I find exciting is that
for some people, the skills and
[Translation failed] for some people, the skills and
knowledge they're taking on could lead
[Translation failed] knowledge they're taking on could lead
to new career paths, new opportunities.
[Translation failed] to new career paths, new opportunities.
It could be the start of something
[Translation failed] It could be the start of something
really big. To learn for free on
[Translation failed] really big. To learn for free on
Brilliant for a full 30 days, go to
[Translation failed] Brilliant for a full 30 days, go to
brilliant.org/numberfile
[Translation failed] brilliant.org/numberfile
or scan that QR code there on screen or
[Translation failed] or scan that QR code there on screen or
of course there'll be a link in the
[Translation failed] of course there'll be a link in the
description. Brilliant's also giving our
[Translation failed] description. Brilliant's also giving our
viewers 20% off an annual premium
[Translation failed] viewers 20% off an annual premium
subscription which will give you
[Translation failed] subscription which will give you
unlimited daily access to everything on
[Translation failed] unlimited daily access to everything on
their site and apply
[Translation failed] their site and apply
new I guess and uh yeah with
[Translation failed] new I guess and uh yeah with
with the with these kind of prime
[Translation failed] with the with these kind of prime
numbers there is no software to see for
[Translation failed] numbers there is no software to see for
them so um I try with my limited
[Translation failed] them so um I try with my limited
programming skills as as
[Translation failed] programming skills as as
Matt um says all the time it's like
[Translation failed] Matt um says all the time it's like
terrible Python code In my case, it's
[Translation failed] terrible Python code In my case, it's
terrible CC
[Translation failed] terrible CC